<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preach'd to the Society for Reformation of Manners in Nottingham Novemb. 24. 1698. By John Barret Minister of the Gospel. Published at the desire of the said Society.</title>
            <author>Barret, John, 1631-1713.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 85 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A78191</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B910C</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R229513</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99899280</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99899280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">152820</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A78191)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 152820)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2323:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preach'd to the Society for Reformation of Manners in Nottingham Novemb. 24. 1698. By John Barret Minister of the Gospel. Published at the desire of the said Society.</title>
                  <author>Barret, John, 1631-1713.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 59, [3] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Tho. Snowden, and sold by John Richards, bookseller in Nottingham,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Novemb. 24. 1698." is in square brackets on the title page.</note>
                  <note>With advertisements at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Dr. Williams' Library, London, England.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Manners and customs --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:152820:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preach'd to the SOCIETY FOR <hi>Reformation of</hi> Manners IN <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>[<hi>Novemb.</hi> 24. 1698.]</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN BARRET</hi> Miniſter of the GOSPEL.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed at the deſire of the ſaid Society.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Snowden,</hi> and ſold by <hi>Iohn Richards,</hi> Bookſeller in <hi>Notting<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:152820:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:152820:2"/>
            <head>A SERMON FOR THE Reformation of Manners.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>AMOS v. xv.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Hate the Evil, and love the Good, and Eſtabliſh Judgment in the Gate: It may be that the Lord God of Hoſts will be Gracious unto the Remnant of <hi>Joſeph.</hi>
                  </p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THough the <hi>Fruit of the Tree</hi> of Knowledge of Good and E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil was <hi>very bitter,</hi> and ſet Mans Teeth on Edge; yet the right Knowledge of Good and Evil is good and neceſſary; without which
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:152820:3"/>we cannot hate the Evil and love the Good.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Difference</hi> of <hi>Moral</hi> Good and Evil is invariable. For any to conceit Virtue and Vice <hi>of an indif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Nature</hi> in themſelves; that the former is only good, becauſe command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; and the latter only evil, as forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, is certainly a moſt wild, and very falſe conceit. Or to imagine, that the Holy God (of His <hi>abſolute Soveraignty</hi>) might have commanded us to deſpiſe His infinitely Glorious Majeſty, to blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheme His moſt Sacred and Reverend Name, and to be unjuſt, intemperate, to run into all exceſs of Riot, to make Beaſts of our ſelves, to be Lewd and Debauch'd, to work all unclean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with greedineſs: Or to imagine, that he might have <hi>prohibited</hi> our liv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Soberly, Righteouſly, and Godly in the World; ſurely ſuch thoughts would be horribly injurious to the <hi>Holy one of Iſrael,</hi> moſt impious and blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous thoughts. They that could en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertain ſuch thoughts of God, would <hi>ſhew themſelves no Chriſtians;</hi> while thus they would <hi>ſubvert</hi> all Religion: Such
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:152820:3"/>would not <hi>ſhew themſelves Men;</hi> but rather to have put off all Reaſon and Humanity: Such would <hi>ſhew themſelves Enemies to Mankind,</hi> who cared not to turn the World upſide down, cared not to turn Human Societies into Herds of brute Beaſts: Yea, ſuch would <hi>inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pretatively,</hi> and by <hi>conſequence</hi> deny that there is a God, that Ruleth and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in the Earth. As ſuch Laws would be moſt contradictory to the Infinite Goodneſs and Holineſs of God. And if He were not infinitely Good and Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, he ſhould not be God. Deny His perfect Holineſs, and you deny Him to be God.</p>
            <p>Yet note (by the way) that beſides thoſe things, which are <hi>intrinſically</hi> good or evil; there are other things <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different</hi> in themſelves; which paſſing under the ſtamp of Divine Authority, the Lord requiring them, they thus be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come unqueſtionable Duties; or for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bidding other of them, they are Sins; till ſuch injunction or prohibition be taken off. And it muſt needs be thus, upon that <hi>Fundamental,</hi> undeniable <hi>Principle,</hi> That God, our Maker, Own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:152820:4"/>and Supreme Ruler and Governour, hath a <hi>Sovereign Right</hi> of commanding, and that Man is under an <hi>indiſputable Obligation</hi> to obey Him in all his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands. That 'tis unqueſtionably good to yield obedience even to ſuch <hi>poſitive</hi> Commands; But evil to tranſgreſs and violate them.</p>
            <p>As God made Man a Reaſonable Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and Upright, after his own I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mage; while Man kept his integrity, there was a right underſtanding and good accord betwixt God and Man, (Mans will being fully conform to the will of his Maker.) Thus at firſt <hi>Mans Nature was fram'd</hi> to love the good, and to hate evil. And nothing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous to right Reaſon, than that it ſhould be ſo.</p>
            <p>And therefore wicked Men in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture are commonly called <hi>Fools,</hi> (a <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Name for them</hi>) as wanting the <hi>right uſe</hi> of Reaſon: As loving that, which in all reaſon they ſhould hate and abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minate; and hating that, which they ought to love. Which ſhews the hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible depravation of Mans Nature by and ſince the Fall. Oh the monſtrous defor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:152820:4"/>of ſinful Souls! what lamenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, horrible diſorders are here! As Sinners <hi>love ſimplicity,</hi> and <hi>hate know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> (<hi>Prov.</hi> 1.22.) <hi>Love Darkneſs and hate the Light,</hi> (as chap. 3. of the Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſt St. <hi>John,</hi> ver. 19, 20. Love their baſe Luſts, and hate Holineſs.</p>
            <p>Unto ſuch a fooliſh, croſs-grain'd, froward and perverſe People was the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> here ſent. The Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> the Houſe of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> for whom (together with their Brethren the Children of <hi>Judah</hi>) the Lord had done more than for all the Families of the Earth beſides. When yet they <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quited Him evil for good;</hi> they went on provoking Him with their manifold Tranſgreſſions, and their mighty Sins, (as here <hi>ver.</hi> 12.) For which they are ſeverely threatned.</p>
            <p>Yet here behold, and wonder. Oh, ſhould we not wonder at the goodneſs and mercy of God ſhewn towards ſuch provoking Creatures as Sinners are! The Lord with His ſharpeſt <hi>reproofs</hi> and ſevereſt <hi>threatnings,</hi> is pleas'd to inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mix moſt gracious <hi>Calls</hi> and <hi>Counſels</hi> to repent and turn; that ſo he might re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:152820:5"/>of the evil threatned, and turn from His fierce Anger; yea, that he might be <hi>gracious unto the Remnant of</hi> Joſeph: According to that, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 33.11. As I live, ſaith the Lord God, I have no plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure in the Death of the wicked, but, <hi>&amp;c</hi> What various methods doth he take to bring ſinners to a better paſs; that iniquity may not be their ruine? His patience and goodneſs is to lead them to Repentance. His inflicting leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer judgments (as warning-pieces) is, that if they take warning and turn unto the Lord that ſmiteth them, greater e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vils may be prevented, ſeverer ſtrokes may be kept off, more waſting Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, Land-deſolating Judgments may be turned away. And ſtill he follows them with gracious, earneſt <hi>Calls,</hi> and and with ſweet encouraging <hi>Promiſes,</hi> (if any means might work on them.) As here, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5, 6. <hi>Seek ye me, and ye ſhall live.</hi> But ſeek not <hi>Bethel</hi>— Seek the Lord and ye ſhall live. And <hi>v.</hi> 14, 15. <hi>Seek good and not evil,</hi> that ye may live; and ſo the Lord, the God of Hoſts ſhall be with you—<hi>Hate the evil, and love the good, and eſtabliſh judgment in the Gate,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:152820:5"/>
            <p> Here is a <hi>Sovereign Remedy</hi> preſcrib'd to, and for a People in a moſt dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Caſe. When judgment was to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards them, the Decree ready to bring forth, Sentence ready to be executed. And 'tis the Lords own preſcription (who is called their <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> Exod. 15.26.)</p>
            <p>Here's a threefold Duty requir'd;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Hate the Evil. 2. Love the good. 3. Eſtabliſh Judgment in the Gate.</p>
            <p>And Gods mercy held forth, or pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mis'd thereupon, [<hi>It may be that the Lord God of Hoſts will be gracious unto the Remnant of</hi> Joſeph.] Which, tho ſpoken of with a <hi>[may be]</hi> yet all the doubt was, whether they would Repent and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form; not whether God would be gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious to them if they did ſo; See <hi>Jer.</hi> 18.7, 8.</p>
            <p>What needeth explanation, I may take notice of as I go on.</p>
            <p>Theſe four Axioms, or Propoſitions I take to lie plain in the Text, that he that runneth may obſerve and take notice of,</p>
            <p n="1">I. 'Tis Gods expreſs Charge, Will and Command that Men hate Evil.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:152820:6"/> II. So likewiſe, That they love that which is good.</p>
            <p n="3">III. And that (according to their pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er and capacity) they eſtabliſh Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Gate.</p>
            <p n="4">IV. And this way a People may hope to find Grace and Favour with the Lord, to the preventing or removing of judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; and for the continuing and further conferring of His mercies. That as it is, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.23. <hi>The Lord bleſs thee, O Habitation of Juſtice, and Mountain of Holineſs;</hi> the Bleſſing of the Lord ſhould be on ſuch a People.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To begin with the firſt of theſe, That 'tis Gods expreſs charge and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand that we hate evil.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. What kind of evil are we to underſtand here?</p>
            <p>Anſw. Not meer <hi>Natural</hi> or <hi>Penal</hi> evil; but <hi>Moral</hi> or <hi>culpable</hi> evil. We muſt <hi>kiſs the Rod,</hi> accept of the Puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our Iniquity, (<hi>Lev.</hi> 26.41.) but hate thoſe ill manners, that are diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing to the Lord, and are wont, or likely to bring us under the Rod. Hate Sin which is the <hi>evil of evils,</hi> the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt evil.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:152820:6"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. How are we to hate it?</p>
            <p>Anſw. There is a twofold hatred:
<list>
                  <item>1. An hatred of <hi>Averſation.</hi> Thus we muſt hate ſin, as having an <hi>Antipa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy</hi> unto it. Hate it ſo as to ſhun and avoid it, all we can.</item>
                  <item>2. An hatred of <hi>Oppoſition.</hi> From an enmity to ſin, not barely ſhunning it, but ſtriving earneſtly againſt it. Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting our ſelves againſt Sin, (as real enemies to it) both <hi>in our ſelves,</hi> and <hi>in others.</hi> And ſurely, they that are reconciled to God, and at peace with Him; they that are Friends to Chriſt, cannot but be Enemies to Sin.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Now this, and the two following Duties are included in the very <hi>Law of Nature.</hi> Theſe are common <hi>Principles of Natural Religion.</hi> But we, who have Gods will more clearly revealed to us in his written word, ſhall be left more in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>excuſable, if we conform not to his will herein. What can be more plain than that, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 97.10. <hi>Ye that Love the Lord, Hate Evil?</hi> So then, none ſhould have a face to ſay, They love God, who do not hate Sin in their Hearts. And how plain is that, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.9. <hi>Abhor that
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:152820:7"/>which is evil.</hi> Where the word' <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> is emphatical. Abhor it even a Hell it ſelf.</p>
            <p>And great reaſon for this ſtrict In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Foraſmuch as God hates Sin. <hi>'Tis the abominable thing which he hates:</hi> Nothing in the world ſo odious to him as Sin. May it not be ſaid, that Sin (in ſome reſpects) is more odious than the very Devils? Theſe (as they are Gods Creatures) have ſome Natural good in them; whereas there is nothing but evil in Sin. And <hi>propter quod unum quod<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> tale eſt, illud eſt magis tale.</hi> It is only for Sin that the Devils are ſuch odi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Creatures in His pure Eyes. Now as God hates Sin, ought not we herein to be <hi>Followers of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) We cannot love the Lord in ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, if we do not hate Sin. Now this is the Firſt and Great Command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart.</hi> Which is a thing impoſſible without an hatred of Sin. <hi>[Ye that Love the Lord, Hate Evil.]</hi> Sin is ſuch an Enemy to God, ſo contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to His moſt Pure and Holy Nature,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:152820:7"/>and to His moſt Righteous will; ſo op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to his Intereſt, to his Honour and Glory; that if we have the love of God in us, we muſt neceſſarily hate and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor Sin, for its <hi>contrariety to God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">(3.) And certainly 'tis a great Duty alſo incumbent on us, to Fear the Lord: [<hi>Thou ſhalt Fear the Lord thy God,</hi> and Serve him. Fear ye not me, ſaith the Lord? If I be a Maſter, where is my Fear?] But there is no true fear of God without an hatred of Sin, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.13. <hi>The Fear of the Lord is to hate Evil,</hi> Pſal. 36.1. The tranſgreſſion of the wicked ſaith within my heart, that there is no fear of God before their Eyes.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) And 'tis as certain, that with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out an hatred of Sin, we ſhall <hi>do no exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution on it.</hi> Now Sin is ſuch a deadly Enemy, that here we muſt <hi>Kill or be Kill'd.</hi> Oh, it <hi>warreth againſt our Souls!</hi> And till we hate it, we ſhall at moſt but <hi>Fence</hi> or <hi>Skirmiſh with it, not Fight in good earneſt againſt it.</hi> What is it, only to ſcratch its face, to raiſe its skin? This will not indanger its Life at all.</p>
            <p>The ſurface of a meer outward Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation is far ſhort of the work of Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:152820:8"/>There is no wounding Sin to the Heart, till we hate it. Indeed the love of Sin is the very life of it: But hatred ſeeks the deſtruction of its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my. And without hating Sin, we ſhall not be for mortifying it. And if we are for ſparing the Life of Sin, our Lives muſt go for its Life.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) We cannot have the <hi>Complacen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial love</hi> of God, till we hate Sin. There is at leaſt a <hi>Secret League</hi> with Sin, till we come to hate it. Never till then, that our league with ſin is broken: And 'tis certain that till our League with Sin is broken, God and our Souls are not agreed. While in League with Sin, there's no Reconciliation, no Peace with God. See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.16, 18. and <hi>ch.</hi> 59.2.</p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Upon the whole, this is a <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criminating Note</hi> and <hi>Mark,</hi> neceſſary to diſtinguiſh true Converts (ſuch as indeed turn from Sin unto God, to dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference them) from the wicked, from Hypocrites. Theſe may abſtain from many Sins; but not from a <hi>right prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple.</hi> A wicked Man may refrain from the outward act of many Sins, either
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:152820:8"/>upon ſome pang and horror of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, or upon ſome Worldly account; when he is far from loathing and hating them, He has a love to them ſtill: But fear of wrath to come; or fear of loſs, ſhame or other puniſhment in this world lays a reſtraint upon him. 'Tis part of the <hi>Deſcription and Character</hi> of a wicked Man, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 36.4. <hi>He abhorreth not evil:</hi> And 'tis enough to prove one wicked ſtill. A bare abſtinence from Sin, will not prove one a true Convert; but there muſt alſo be a real abhorrence of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> I. That the Lord hath given ſuch expreſs charge to hate evil; then is it not manifeſt that they are here condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, who indeed are direct <hi>Antipodes</hi> to this Divine Command, who ſtand in <hi>Diametrical oppoſition to it?</hi> I mean ſuch as hate the good, inſtead of hating evil. Alas! how many <hi>hate the Light,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their deeds are evil? How many <hi>that hate him that rebuketh in the Gate,</hi> and abhor him that ſpeaketh uprightly? (As here <hi>v.</hi> 10.) How many that hate Inſtruction, and that hate <hi>Reformation?</hi> (even hate <hi>both the Name and Thing!</hi>)
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:152820:9"/>How many that hate Holineſs, and hate Gods Saints and Servants for that for which the Holy Pſalmiſt profeſſeth his great delight was in them, (<hi>Pſal.</hi> 16.3.) their excelling in Virtue? <hi>Bear wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,</hi> (Sirs) bear witneſs: Are not ſuch notorious Deſpiſers of Gods Command: Yea, do not ſuch ſhew themſelves haters of God? Oh, what height of Impiety is this!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> II. This ſhould put us upon ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Self-Examination, and on a ſtrict Enquiry into our Hearts whether we indeed hate evil. And great need of an impartial ſearch here, that we be not deceived and miſtaken Then,</p>
            <p n="1">(1. Have we an <hi>hatred of ſin, as ſin?</hi> As 'tis an offence againſt God, a tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the holy Law of God, our Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor and Redeemer. As right ſorrow for Sin is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>according to God,</hi> (2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.9.) So the true hatred of Sin is with reſpect unto God. To have an Averſation from ſome ſinful practices; <hi>not as forbidden in Gods word;</hi> but upon o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Foreign Accounts, (<hi>v.</hi> 9.) As ſuch practices would croſs our worldly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns, and interfere with our carnal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſts;
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:152820:9"/>this will not prove that we <hi>hate Sin;</hi> but only that we <hi>love our Cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit</hi> and Reputation, our worldly profit and the like. Again, ſome that have no deteſtation of Sin, yet dare not take that liberty in ſinning as formerly; being checked with a fearful apprehenſion and expectation of the Puniſhment threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and due to Sin. 'Tis one thing to <hi>hate Sin;</hi> and another to <hi>dread the ſad</hi> and <hi>bitter conſequents</hi> thereof. The Conſcience of a Natural Man is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſtartled and awakened, while his will is not renew'd, his heart not changed.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Have we an hatred of all and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very known Sin: <hi>A quatenus ad omne</hi>— If we hate Sin as Sin; then it will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low that we hate all Sin, known to us. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>Hatred is againſt the whole kind.</hi> One that hates a Toad as venemous, cannot but hate other Creatures, that he knows to be like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe venemous. Here is <hi>one difference</hi> betwixt a Natural and a Regenerate Man; <hi>viz.</hi> A Natural Man may ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtain from ſome Sins, though he does not truly hate any Sin; which is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent,
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:152820:10"/>in that he freely alloweth of other Sins, he knows are no leſs forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den; yea, he <hi>will not part with them:</hi> But a Regenerate Man, though he can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not live here free from Sin; yet he does not live in any known Sin; for that Sin is the <hi>evil he hates,</hi> and that he would gladly get rid of.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) A real hatred of Sin is abiding and conſtant. This is one <hi>difference</hi> betwixt <hi>Hatred</hi> and <hi>Anger.</hi> If one is only angry at another, the angry fit may be over in a little time. As two Friends may fall out ſometimes; and yet ſoon be very good Friends again. But where hatred is, that admits not of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation. And if I be not miſtaken Dr. <hi>Preſton</hi> hath this expreſſion, <q>
                  <hi>'Tis an ill Sign to fall out with Sin, and grow Friends again.</hi>
               </q> Some indeed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der preſent gripes and pangs of Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, ſeem to be for putting away their Luſts: But that ſick, ſhaking fit is no ſooner over, than they return to 'em again, <hi>as the Dog to his vomit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Hatred is implacable, and dead<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. It ſeeks the deſtruction of that we hate. So if we hate Sin indeed, we
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:152820:10"/>are for purſuing it to the Death. We can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not reſt while it has a being in us. We ſet our ſelves againſt it, to mortifie it more and more.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) If we hate Sin indeed, we cannot but be moved when we ſee it breaking forth in others As <hi>Lot</hi> we ſhall vex our Souls at the ſight, and at the thoughts of that abounding wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>edneſs in the World, in this our Land. And as we have occaſion and opportunity, we ſhall reprove Sinners, and indeavour to give check to Sin, what in us lieth; as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 75.4, 5. <hi>I ſaid unto the Fools, deal not fooliſhly;</hi> and to <hi>the wicked, lift not up the Horn.</hi> How can we ſay we hate Sin, if we care not tho' ſinners go on in their Evil ways; if we will not endeavour to put a ſtop to them when we might?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> III.<note place="margin">This Uſe, with the next Propoſition (though prepar'd) I did but glanſe at in the Sermon Preach'd to the Society.</note> Be we exhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to hate Sin? And if we do hate it, labour after a more <hi>intenſe degree</hi> of ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred, to have our Hearts more ſet againſt Sin. O Chriſtians, as you love the Lord, and as you love your ſelves, and as you love <hi>England,</hi> hate evil.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) If you love the Lord; how can you but hate Sin? If we have the love of God, ſhall we not then <hi>fear to offend him?</hi> And ſhall we not hate that which we know to be an Offence to him? And ſhall we not be
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:152820:11"/>grieved to ſee others diſhonour and provoke him? And ſhall not our Hearts riſe at any indignities offer'd to him? As it was with the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 7.13. <hi>Will ye weary my God alſo?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if we love him, then ſhall we not hate Sin, as that which formerly <hi>ſeparated betwixt God and our Souls?</hi> And as that which would obſtruct or interrupt our Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with him, and may provoke him to withdraw, may deprive us of his moſt comforting preſence? And are we not like to <hi>loſe the ſenſe of his love,</hi> if we are a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bating and more remiſſe in our hatred of Sin?</p>
            <p>And if we love him, then ſhall we not count his Enemies our Enemies? And be hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily diſpleas'd at the wrongs done to him, as at any injuries done to us?</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) If you love your own Souls, muſt you not then hate Sin? Why, you have <hi>no ſuch Enemy</hi> in all the World again. We ſuffer more by Sin than by all other Enemies (Men or Devils.) All that they can do would but <hi>Exerciſe</hi> us; not really hurt and endamage our Souls; ſo long as we are not inſtigated or drawn to Sin by them.</p>
            <p>But this is moſt certain, till we hate Sin, we are Enemies to our own Souls. We are <hi>in league with our Souls utter Enemy.</hi> And without turning from our Sins, we ſhall die in our Sins. Now there is no real turning from Sin, without having our Hearts turn'd
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:152820:11"/>againſt it, without hating it. While the <hi>heart goes out ſecretly</hi> after any Luſt in Gods ſight, and account we <hi>live in that Sin;</hi> tho' our outward carriage may be ſuch that Men may not have the leaſt ſuſpicion of our being guilty of it.</p>
            <p>And then except we hate Sin, <hi>our iniquity</hi> (ſurely) <hi>will be found to be hateful.</hi> When the Lord ſhall at laſt reckon with us, reprove us, and ſet our Sins in order before our Eyes; Oh! then we ſhall ſee how we did but <hi>flat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter our ſelves;</hi> and ſee how wofully Sin deceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us; ſee how hateful and odious a thing Sin is, notwithſtanding we were <hi>very fond</hi> of it; or though we thought there was no great harm in it.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) If you love the Land and Nation, if you <hi>wiſh well to</hi> England, hate Evil. Alas, do not our great <hi>culpable Evils,</hi> our high provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cations threaten to return upon our Heads; and fall upon the Land in ſad <hi>penal evils,</hi> in ſore and heavy Judgments! 'Tis a notable paſſage that Biſhop <hi>Hall</hi> relates of a noble Captain, who was earneſtly ſollicited to take on him the Defence of a ſtrong City, ſtor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with Plenty of Ammunition, and fortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with impregnable Walls: <q>
                  <hi>Yea, but</hi> (ſays he) <hi>have you any covering betwit it and Heaven?</hi> Have you <hi>any defence againſt the Vengeance of that God whom your Sins have provoked?</hi>
               </q> The Application of the ſtory is this, <q>
                  <hi>In vain ſhall we think to ſecure our
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:152820:12"/>Selves and our State from Earth,</hi> if we ir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritate Heaven.</q> And let me tell you, <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Sins are more dangerous and likely to be more miſchievous than any Foreign Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my could be. For our manifold Sins and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations (without a more <hi>General Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> than is yet to be ſeen amongſt us) the Lord, <hi>the Lord God of Hoſts</hi> may be <hi>provok'd to become our Enemy.</hi> And where are we then? What will become of us if we have him our Enemy? As it follows, <hi>Amos</hi> 9.5. <hi>The Lord God of Hoſts is he that toucheth the Land;</hi> and it ſhall melt, and all that dwell therein ſhall mourn, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> See <hi>Nehem.</hi> 1.5, 6. I muſt tell you, if you do not hate Sin, if you are not <hi>Enemies to Sin;</hi> you can be <hi>no true Friends to</hi> England. But I may dwell no longer on this; and muſt haſt over the ſecond Propoſition, which follows.</p>
            <p n="2">II. We are as expreſly charg'd and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded to <hi>love that which is good.</hi> As 'tis not enough to leave off, and ſhun evil practices; but we muſt hate the Evil: So 'tis not enough to do good actions; but we muſt love the Good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 1. What are we to underſtand by [Good] here?</p>
            <p>Anſw. Not any falſe or Phantaſtick Good, Not what is only good in ſhew and appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance; or in a Sinners deluded fancy: Not the Covetous Worldlings good: Not the Senſualiſts good. No need of a <hi>Command</hi> to love Earthly Riches, or Carnal Pleaſures,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:152820:12"/>which Carnal Hearts are too much in love with: But need enough of a <hi>Caution</hi> or <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hibition</hi> againſt ſetting our Hearts on theſe. Which indeed we meet with again and again in Gods Holy Word.</p>
            <p>But the <hi>Good</hi> we are required to love, <hi>ſtands in oppoſition to the Evil we muſt hate.</hi> Therefore look as whatſoever the Law for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bids, we are to hate as Evil: So whatſoever He requires we are to love as Good. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever is right and good in Gods Eyes ſhould be ſo in ours. He that is <hi>Wiſdom it ſelf,</hi> and <hi>Goodneſs it ſelf,</hi> cannot deceive or <hi>miſinform</hi> us concerning what is Good.</p>
            <p>Indeed he is the prime good, to be firſt and principally loved. For that he is <hi>Sum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me Bonus, &amp; ſummum Bonum;</hi> ſuperlative<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, moſt tranſcendently good; <hi>the chiefeſt good.</hi> He is Eſſentially, Originally, Infinite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, Immutably Good. He is Goodneſs it ſelf. And here is <hi>the Root of the Matter.</hi> To lay a <hi>right Foundation,</hi> we muſt ſee that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin at the love of God, begin at the love of God in Chriſt, in whom he hath diſcover'd and made himſelf known, <hi>as infinitely ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able:</hi> And then we muſt love other things, according as they are conform to his perfect Holy Nature, and ſo far as is agreeable to his Good and Righteous will.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> 2. What is it <hi>to love the Good?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Anſw. In ſhort, loving the Good is the <hi>complacency of the Soul</hi> in that which is good,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:152820:13"/>whereby the Soul embraceth, and cleaves to that which is good, is knit to it as one with it, and would by no means be parted from it; but ſtill follows that which is good, and has a care to hold it faſt. Here you have a brief Account of the <hi>Affection</hi> together with its <hi>proper Effects.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now what could be more reaſonable and equitable than this Precept, <hi>Love the good?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Great reaſon for it from <hi>the very Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the thing.</hi> Indeed theſe Precepts in the Text are ſuch <hi>common Principles,</hi> as all, who would not <hi>out-face the very light of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,</hi> muſt neceſſarily yield their Aſſent unto. All that would <hi>ſhew themſelves Men,</hi> muſt grant, that there is <hi>no place at all for Hatred;</hi> if it ſhould not be turn'd againſt that which is evil: ſo <hi>no place to be found for love;</hi> if not to be ſet on that which is good. As in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed <hi>contrariorum contraria eſt ratio;</hi> There is as good reaſon for our loving the one, as for our hating the other. Nothing more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruous to Reaſon, than to love that which is good. <hi>Omnis Appetitus fertur in Bonum.</hi> And tho' the <hi>Senſitive Appetite</hi> looks at a lower kind of good; yet ſurely the Will, the <hi>Rational Appetite</hi> ſhould look higher. Does not every Man's reaſon tell him, that of two ſorts of good, the better ſhould be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd, the <hi>greater good ſhould be choſen?</hi> And certainly, where the ſenſitive Appetite (that ſhould be under the Conduct and <hi>Regimen</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:152820:13"/>of Reaſon) beareth ſway, will not be rul'd, it ſhews ſuch Men ſo far <hi>brutified,</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the right uſe of Reaſon. And if that which is truly, really good, ſhould attract our Wills and Affections, before a meer ſeeming good; then ſhould not <hi>naked Vertue</hi> be preferr'd and choſen before Vice in its richeſt Robes. Tho' Vertue had no dowry here; yet were ſhe not to be embraced, rather than any vicious courſe, notwithſtanding it promiſed one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms upon Earth, with the glory of them. Surely, Goodneſs is the proper Object of Love, the formal Reaſon of it, the Load<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of it. And they that love not Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, ſhew themſelves monſtrouſly deprav'd.</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Without loving that which is good, 'tis certain, we cannot be good. We may do things good in themſelves; but if not <hi>from a love to Goodneſs;</hi> but only for ſome by ends, out of Siniſter Reſpects, our Hearts may be ſtark nought. They that are truly good, have a ſincere love to Goodneſs. They love it <hi>propter ſe,</hi> for its goodneſs ſake. That which is good, is very grateful, pleaſing, and ſuitable to a good Heart.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) There is no good we do that's pleaſing unto God, if it be not from a love to that which is good. Without this we act not from a right Principle, nor <hi>to a right end.</hi> Which things the Lord looks chiefly at, more than at the bare outward Action.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Without a love to that which is good, we cannot follow that which is good, (as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:152820:14"/>we ought to do, 3 Epiſtle of the Apoſtle <hi>John, v.</hi> 11.) neither are we like to <hi>cleave to that which is good,</hi> (a Duty requir'd, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12.9.) nor ſhall we <hi>hold faſt that which is good,</hi> (1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5.21.) without cleaving to it in Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, we are not like to keep cloſe to it in our Practice. Satan, that grand Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, with wicked Men, <hi>his Agents,</hi> will do all they can to diſcourage, and draw us off from that which is good; and to allure, and draw us on to that which is evil. 'Tis the property of wicked Men, <hi>that they would have all as had as themſelves;</hi> and the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perty of Satan, that he would have all as miſerable as himſelf: and being void of all Goodneſs, but as full of Wickedneſs as he can hold, hence he envies us, having not any ſpark of goodneſs, or any inclination towards it.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) It is unqueſtionably our Duty to hate evil (as we heard before.) And it is by the <hi>Love of Goodneſs,</hi> that we come to hate evil. When we hate evil, we hate it, as being oppoſite and contrary to the good, which the Lord hath requir'd, taught us to love, hath inclin'd our Hearts to Love.</p>
            <p>Now what Uſe are we to make of this? Tho' I muſt be very brief.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> I. Hence we may infer, That there is a ſpecial Love due to thoſe that are good. A ſpecial love due to them, even for the good that is in them, and the good ſuch do in the World. Such are indeed <hi>Benefactors</hi> to the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:152820:14"/>World (tho' lightly eſteem'd.) But 'tis the Duty not only of a Biſhop (as 'tis one Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lification ſet down, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.8.) but of every Chriſtian as well, to be a <hi>Lover of good Men.</hi> True, we ought to love all Men, for ſo much good as is in them, and with a <hi>Love of Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volence.</hi> Bear no Malice to any Man. Chriſt has taught us to love our Enemies. And we muſt <hi>love the Perſons</hi> of the Wicked, tho' we are to hate <hi>their wicked Practices.</hi> But we are not to love all Men alike. There is a <hi>ſpecial Love of Complacence</hi> owing to good Men. Our delight muſt be in thoſe that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel in Vertue. I queſtion whether Satan was ever at any time more buſie, than in this Age of ours, to divide the Hearts of ſuch. But, bleſſed be God, his Name be praiſed, that we can ſee the Enemy's Deſign croſs'd any where. That in ſome places the Primitive Spirit of True Chriſtian Love ſeems to be reviving.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> II. <hi>A word of Exhortation.</hi> O Love-the Good!</p>
            <p>O how ought we to <hi>love God, who is Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs it ſelf!</hi> Love him above all; Love him for himſelf; Love other Things and Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons only <hi>in God,</hi> and <hi>for him.</hi> And thus all our love ſhould <hi>center</hi> and <hi>terminate in him.</hi> Remember the firſt and great Commandment, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22.37. <hi>Thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy Heart, and with all thy Soul, and with all thy Mind.</hi> And all is too little: God being infinitely Good and Amiable, ſurely he
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:152820:15"/>deſerves more Love, than our Hearts can hold, than all the Powers and Faculties of our Souls ever can expreſs.</p>
            <p>And how ought we to love a good and gracious Redeemer, the Lord Jeſus Chriſt! <hi>He is altogether lovely;</hi> Full of Grace and Truth. How can we think of his own <hi>Love<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs,</hi> as being the Brightneſs of his Fathers Glory, and the expreſs Image of his Perſon, (<hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3.) and how can we think of his won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derful <hi>unparallel'd Love to us,</hi> and not have our Hearts enamour'd of him, enflam'd with Love to him again? Oh! what wicked Hearts have they, that are in love with their vain and ſinful Pleaſures; or are doting on the Worlds Riches or Honours; but have not the Love of God in them; nor do they love the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in ſincerity, in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of whom, nothing in the World is to be lov'd! But is it not good to love God and Jeſus Chriſt? And ſhould we not <hi>love to love</hi> the higheſt, the moſt perfect Objects of Love; to whom our moſt ardent love, were it raiſed to the higheſt degree poſſible, were ſtill far from being adaequate?</p>
            <p>And then ſhould we not <hi>love the good word of God?</hi> What ſervent love doth the Holy Pſalmiſt expreſs to the Word, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119. Yea, ſays he, <hi>v.</hi> 140. <hi>Thy word is very pure: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thy Servant loveth it.</hi> We ſhould be at a ſad loſs, to know what is good, were it not <hi>for the Word.</hi> But there the Lord ſheweth us <hi>what is good, Mic.</hi> 6.8.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:152820:15"/>
               <hi>Wo unto them that call evil good, and good evil,</hi> (<hi>Iſa.</hi> 5.20.) And ſuch <hi>woful Miſtakes</hi> are Men like to fall into, that either have not God's Word, or regard it not, take not good heed to the word. But if God's Teſtimonies are our Meditation, our Delight, and the Men of our Counſel; if we be not unskilful in the word of Righteouſneſs, but have our Senſes exerciſed therein; we may thereby diſcern both good and evil. And obſerve it, <hi>according to our Love to God's word,</hi> ſuch will be our hatred of evil, and our love to that which is good, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 119.113, 163.</p>
            <p>Again, the <hi>Lord's Day that's a good Day.</hi> A day which God hath ſet apart for his ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Service; and which he is wont to bleſs (above other days) unto thoſe, that have a care to keep it Holy. Oh! love and prize the Chriſtian Sabbath, count it a delight!</p>
            <p>Love God's Publick Worſhip. <hi>How ami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are thy Tabernacles, O Lord of Hoſts!</hi> Think, how we are priviledg'd above our Brethren in <hi>France,</hi> &amp;c. How happy would they think themſelves, might they enjoy the like Liberty of attending on God's Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; and if there were none to interrupt them, or to make them afraid!</p>
            <p>And love Family-Worſhip. Keep that up daily, Morning and Night. Let your Houſes be little Churches: And if you count God's Service perfect Freedom; ſure, you will alſo delight in ſecret Duties, where you may have greater Liberty in Prayer.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:152820:16"/>
            <p> Love Holineſs and the power of Godli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs. Alas, how many take up with a meer Form of Godlineſs! but do you take heed of reſting there.</p>
            <p>Love a Religious Strictneſs, and Exactneſs in your ordinary Converſation. Walk by Rule: A Courſe that Men generally, yea, too many Profeſſors (I fear) are very tardy in.</p>
            <p>Love Righteouſneſs. Hate all unrighte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Dealing. Such as love Violence (or In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſtice) the Lord hateth, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 11.5.</p>
            <p>Love the Truth and Peace, (as <hi>Zach.</hi> 8.19.) <hi>Diligite veritatem paciſicam, &amp; pacem veram, quae ad normam verbi divini, quod eſt veritas, congruit. (Tarnovius.)</hi> Indeed Peace without Truth ſhould not be taking with us. But ſo far as will ſtand with the Intereſt of Truth, we ſhould all be <hi>followers of Peace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Love Mercy. (<hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8.) Delight in doing what good you can. Be beneficial to as many as you can, (as you have opportunity.) <hi>Ubi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunq, homo eſt, ibi beneficio locus eſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay no more here, but as the Apoſtle, <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Whatſoever things are true, whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever things are honeſt, whatſoever things are juſt, whatſoever things are pure, whatſoever things are lovely, whatſoever things are of good Report, if there be any Vertue, if there be any Praiſe, think on theſe things.</hi> Apply your Minds to them, ſet your Hearts on them.</p>
            <p>Which if you do, then know (for your En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement,)</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:152820:16"/> (1.) In loving the good, you ſhall be Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of God; which (as it is your Duty, ſo it) will be <hi>your Honour:</hi> Is it not an ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour to be Followers of God?</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) 'Tis very pleaſing to God. This is the good and acceptable Will of God. And if you love God, certainly it is your unfeigned deſire to pleaſe him, (whether others be plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed or diſpleaſed.) You will think your ſelves happy if you can but pleaſe him.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) This will prove you truly good. Here's a comfortable evidence of your being in a good Eſtate, if indeed you love the Good.</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) And thus you may be aſſured, that the Lord will be good to you. He is good, and does good to ſuch. That your Souls <hi>ſhall lodge in Goodneſs.</hi> And how great is his Goodneſs, that he hath laid up for ſuch! This is (with <hi>Mary</hi>) to chuſe the good part.</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) And if you love, and embrace Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, who (but ſuch as are of a Diabolical Spirit) would ſeek to harm you? But ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe any ſhould ſeek you hurt, for loving and following that which is good; yet you may be of good Courage. The Lord will turn it to good. <hi>Bonis omnia in bonum.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6.) And if you are Lovers of that which is good, you are in the moſt hopeful way to procure, and promote others Weal. You are moſt likely to help to make bad Men good, to make evil Times better, to procure
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:152820:17"/>much good to the Societies which you are Members of, and to keep off Publick Evils.</p>
            <p>But I beſeech you, ſee that you be <hi>true lovers of Goodneſs,</hi> even <hi>eo nomine</hi> as goodneſs; and ſo lovers of all that is truly good. As we muſt hate all evil, hate every falſe way; ſo muſt we love all that is good, love every good path. <hi>Partiality would bewray Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſie.</hi> When the Heart is indeed gain'd to the love of that which is good; it is for the whole of real goodneſs; not barely for the <hi>Liſts or for a few Shreads</hi> of it. Thus are <hi>Secret Duties</hi> good; what the Lord requires. Then before theſe, as well as for other Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties wherein others joyn with you: And thus you muſt be for <hi>coſtly Duties,</hi> that require more ſelf denyal than ordinary.</p>
            <p>And let me mind you of one thing more, <hi>ſcil.</hi> That Love is a leading Affection and an active Principle. As I remember one calls it, <q>The great Wheel of the Soul, that ſets all agoing.</q> Love will carry out the Soul to the thing loved. Thus if you love that which is good, you will be follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of that which is good, you will cleave to that which is good, you will be promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of that which is good.</p>
            <p>And ſo they that hate the evil and love the good, theſe are the Men who will be <hi>for eſtabliſhing Judgment in the Gate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Gate</hi> of the City was the noted place where the Judges uſed to ſit. As <hi>Lyra</hi> ſays,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:152820:17"/>
               <hi>Sicut praecipitur,</hi> Deut. 16. (v. 18.) <hi>ad hoc ut quilibet tam peregrinus quam civis poſſit ſtatim Judicis invenire.</hi> That as well ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as Citizens might know whither readily to go for Juſtice.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To eſtabliſh Judgment in the Gate,</hi> is to ſee the due adminiſtration of Juſtice; that Juſtice be not neglected nor perverted: but rightly and duly executed. So I come to a Third Propoſition.</p>
            <p n="3">III. Gods will is, that Juſtice and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment have place, and a due courſe amongſt Men.</p>
            <p>And tho' this looks and <hi>points more directly,</hi> and eſpecially towards Rulers, Judges, Civil Magiſtrates; yet others are not to look on themſelves as wholly unconcerned in this matter. Even private perſons (upon many Accounts) are obliged to do what in them lieth, that Judgment may be eſtabliſhed in the Gate.</p>
            <p>Without Queſtion this is a thing that all ought to pray for. All ſhould be <hi>ſending up their Votes</hi> (their Prayers) to Heaven for Rulers, Magiſtrates, that they may keep judgment and do juſtice, that under them we may lead quiet and peaceable lives in all godlineſs and honeſty.</p>
            <p>Again, many private perſons may <hi>have a ſtroke</hi> in eſtabliſhing judgment amongſt us may contribute ſomething towards it, <hi>by giving their Votes</hi> for perſons rightly quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:152820:18"/>when our Repreſentatives are to be choſen, or any are to be Elected into Offices wherein they ſhall have any ſhare in the Government; and by their place be concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (more or leſs) with the diſtribution of Juſtice. And let them look to it, how they will Anſwer it to God and their own Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences, who regard not how they caſt away their Votes in ſuch caſes, on perſons not fit to be truſted (ſo that they can but ſerve their own turns.)</p>
            <p>But further, private perſons ought (as oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion is offered) to encourage and be aſſiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant unto Magiſtrates in the due execution of Juſtice, in the right diſcharge of their Office. And this way may they promote the work of eſtabliſhing Judgment in the Gate. 'Tis a Duty incumbent upon all, <hi>to ſeek Righteouſneſs, Zep.</hi> 2.3. To <hi>ſeek Judgment,</hi> Iſa. 1.17. And 'tis an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy charge brought in againſt the Jews, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.4. <hi>None calleth for Juſtiee.</hi> And the People are not excus'd, as to the Prieſts Male-adminiſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, <hi>Jer.</hi> 5.31. <hi>The Prophets propheſie falſly, &amp; the Prieſts bear rule by their means, and my Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple love to have it ſo.</hi> And we ſee in the Text, that the Lord is ſo for Juſtice and Judgment having a due courſe; that without better care about it, he would not have them think or hope that he would be gracious unto them.</p>
            <p>Now it cannot ſeem ſtrange that he is ſo concerned for Juſtice and Judgment taking place, if we conſider theſe two or three things following;</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:152820:18"/> (1.) <hi>His Honour,</hi> (as he is the <hi>Supream Ruler</hi> of the World) is here concerned. As when Judges, Magiſtrates (on the contrary) wreſt and pervert judgment, bearing down truth and right, as far as they can; countenan<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cing or connivingar impiety, and profaneneſs, which they ought to puniſh and ſuppreſs; and oppreſſing or diſcountenancing true good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and piety, which they ought to protect and promote; theſe things are a great re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach and diſhonour unto God, whoſe <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, Officers and Deputies</hi> they are: 'Tis as if they would have the World believe <hi>that God is altogether ſuch a one as they are.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">(2.) His love to Juſtice, Righteouſneſs and Equity; with his abhorrence of the contrary. He loveth Righteouſneſs and Judgment, <hi>Pſa.</hi> 33.5. and 37.28. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 61.8. <hi>I the Lord love Judgment:</hi> With which compare, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59.14, 15. Judgment is turn'd away back<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward, and Juſtice ſtandeth afar off—. And the Lord ſaw it, and it <hi>diſpleaſed him, that there was no Judgment.</hi> Pro. 17.15. <hi>He that juſtifieth the Wicked, and he that condemneth the Juſt, even they both are abomination to the Lord.</hi> So <hi>woe to ſuch,</hi> Iſa. 5.23.</p>
            <p n="3">(3.) His Love to Mankind, and Care of Humane Societies. How ill can theſe ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt without Judgment? Therefore he would have Judgment eſtabliſhed in the Gate; becauſe <hi>Judgment eſtabliſheth the Land:</hi> Prov. 29.4. <hi>The King by Judgment eſtabliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:152820:19"/>the Land:</hi> Whenas the perverting of Judgment tends to the overthrow of a Land, both <hi>efficiently</hi> and <hi>meritoriouſly.</hi> God hath in favour towards Mankind, for the Preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation and well-being of humane Societies, ordained the Office of Civil Rulers, for ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtring Juſtice, to keep Men in order, or to puniſh Diſorders. What were an <hi>Army,</hi> without Officers, but a <hi>Rout?</hi> So what were a Nation, or City, without Rulers, but a <hi>Mob,</hi> or confuſed Tumult? And tho' ſuch were not aſſaulted with a Foreign Enemy, yet how likely ſoon to come to ruine by <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtine Diſcords?</hi> What lamentable Broils and Tumults would ariſe, without any way or means to appeaſe them? Yea, ſuch is the Degeneracy and Corruption of Mankind, that without Rulers and Civil Government, <hi>better order might be expected amongſt brute Beaſts,</hi> than among Men. Thus Men would come to be <hi>oppreſs'd every one by another, and every one by his Neighbour.</hi> Yea, thus the Eſtates and Lives of the Honeſteſt and Beſt, would lie continually at the Mercy of the Vileſt and Worſt of Men.</p>
            <p>But I muſt think of the <hi>ſpecial occaſion</hi> of our Aſſembling at this time. I am forc'd to to be too ſhort on the former Propoſitions, and prevented going further; tho' there is a 4th Propoſition in the Text before us, which I can only ſpeak to by the by. Only there is one thing, which you ſhould all take
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:152820:19"/>notice of. May you not here ſee the <hi>inexcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſable Folly,</hi> and <hi>great Ingratitude</hi> of Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Sinners, of a Wicked World, that will not be govern'd by God's Laws? <hi>Laws ſo good</hi> in themſelves, ſo good for Men, ſo <hi>bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial to Humane Societies,</hi> were they gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally obſerv'd. Surely this would be the <hi>Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of a Nation</hi> to obſerve God's Righteous Judgments, <hi>Deut.</hi> 4.6. <hi>Keep therefore and do them, for this is your wiſdom</hi> —. So it ſhould be well with them. But what Miſeries and Calamities doth the World groan under, as partly <hi>produc'd,</hi> and partly <hi>procur'd</hi> by the Contempt, and Violation of the ſame?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe.</hi> Now what remains is for <hi>Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion:</hi> And that ſpecially directed unto you, <hi>The Society for Reformation of Manners</hi> in this Town and Corporation (tho' I would not that others ſhould think themſelves uncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern'd here) <hi>Hate the evil, and love the good; and do what in you lieth to eſtabliſh Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in our Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gentlemen, Friends, Brethren,</hi> I can truly ſay, that as my Heart is towards you, who have offer'd your ſelves willingly to this highly neceſſary Service, and my poor, yet hearty Prayers have been for you from your firſt undertaking it; ſo it would rejoyce my Heart, if now the Lord would ſo favour, aſſiſt and ſucceed me, that I might help a little to ſtrengthen your Hands; yea, that I might <hi>ſtrengthen your Hands in God,</hi> (as we
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:152820:20"/>have the expreſſion, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.16.) Well, (Sirs) <hi>take God along with you,</hi> look to him, and his holy Word for Counſel, and aim principally at his Glory, and act from a principle of Love to God and True Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, with an hatred of evil. As tho' you may not <hi>hate any Man's Perſon,</hi> how wicked ſoever; yet the wicked Practices and Enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities of ſuch, you muſt hate and oppoſe. And where milder and more gentle means are <hi>not likely to take effect,</hi> ſhew your hatred thereof in expoſing the guilty to ſhame, and ſuch other Penalties, as may be legally in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted on them. And go on (Sirs) with your worthy Deſign, ſo agreeable to the Law of God, and to the Laws of the Land. <hi>Deal couragiouſly, and the Lord will be with the good,</hi> 2 Chro. 19.11. Thus you will be <hi>doing your part</hi> to eſtabliſh Judgment in the Gate. And as your worthy example hath influen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced ſome already, it may excite and provoke more to their Duty, to help forward this good work of Reformation.</p>
            <p>Let me lay a few things before you, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gage, and encourage you to hold on.</p>
            <p n="1">(1.) Think of the hainouſneſs and odiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of thoſe ſins, which you have a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect, you may give ſome conſiderable check unto, having your Magiſtrates concurrence. As profane <hi>Swearing</hi> and <hi>Curſing,</hi> call'd thoſe <hi>deteſtable ſins,</hi> in the late <hi>Act of Parl.</hi> They are a moſt manifeſt Breach of the 3d
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:152820:20"/>Commandment, in an Heaven-daring man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. A taking God's Name in vain, with a <hi>moſt heavy Accent.</hi> Tho' the Lord hath threatned, <hi>That he will not hold thoſe guilt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs</hi> (but without Repentance, will ſurely puniſh them) <hi>that take his Name in vain.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the ſins of <hi>Drunkenneſs,</hi> and <hi>Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleanneſs,</hi> how odious and abominable are they! Each of them a Reproach to Human Nature. They that ſerve ſuch filthy, brutiſh Luſts, may ſeem to have put off Humanity, to have <hi>degenerated into Beaſts,</hi> tho' in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Shape (which is the more monſtrous.) Such Practices are vile in Heatheniſh Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries; how much more abominable and intollerable in a Chriſtian Kingdom! And what is the open <hi>Prophanation of the Lord's Day leſs,</hi> (I ſay, what is it leſs) than Mens <hi>publiſhing their Impiety,</hi> an <hi>open proclaiming of their Irreligion?</hi> I ſuppoſe none of you could have been ſatisfied to <hi>inform againſt thoſe Religious Meetings,</hi> where no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was taught contrary to the <hi>Doctrine of the Church of</hi> England; and where other parts of Worſhip were the <hi>ſame for ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance</hi> with the Worſhip us'd in the Church of <hi>England,</hi> only differing <hi>as to ſome acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental Modes:</hi> Whereas in the late Times <hi>Informations</hi> were frequently given in againſt ſuch Religious Meetings; while prophane Perſons might, even on the Lord's Day, have frequented Taverns, Ale-houſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:152820:21"/>Without any fear of being diſturb'd. But I queſtion not, you can <hi>readily diſtinguiſh</hi> betwixt that caſe, and the preſent caſe that lieth before you. And you find <hi>Nehemiah</hi> contended with the Nobles <hi>for prophaning the Sabbath-day;</hi> when they <hi>ſuffer'd others to prophane it,</hi> chap. 13.17. <hi>What evil thing is this that ye do, and prophane the Sabbath-day?</hi> He declares againſt it, as <hi>very ill done of them,</hi> that they would connive at, or ſuffer ſuch prophanation of the Sabbath.</p>
            <p>And then, as to <hi>diſorderly Houſes,</hi> how miſchievous, what infectious Places are they! <hi>Seminaries</hi> of Sin and Wickedneſs. <hi>Nets of unclean Birds.</hi> Is it not a good work to help to pull down thoſe Neſts (I mean, to put down ſuch Houſes?) <hi>Places of Infection.</hi> Yea, were it not leſs dangerous to go into a <hi>common Peſt-houſe;</hi> than to haunt ſuch Hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes? 'Tis a <hi>worſe plague</hi> that many catch in ſuch Houſes, to their Souls everlaſting ruine.</p>
            <p>Indeed you muſt hate all evil: but then ſhould you not manifeſt an abhorrence of ſo great Evils; and that when you are in a good Capacity to check and curb them?</p>
            <p n="2">(2.) Think of the neceſſity of your Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting your Magiſtrates, if you would have the Laws againſt Prophaneneſs vigorouſly executed, and would have Juſtice take place againſt ſuch notorious Offences and Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. Certainly, good Laws, if not put in Execution, would ſignifie nothing; would
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:152820:21"/>be as <hi>a Bell without a Clapper.</hi> And Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates of themſelves, (tho' never ſo deſirous to be faithful in their Office, and true to their Oath in puniſhing Offenders, yet) can do little or nothing, without others giving proof of Offences and Crimes committed. Without making <hi>uſe of others Eyes and Ears, their Hands could ſeldom or never ſtrike.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as there's <hi>Honour due</hi> to them, in regard of their Place and Office, ſo likewiſe that <hi>help and aſſiſtance</hi> muſt needs be due, without which they ſhould but <hi>bear the Sword in vain.</hi> And ſo I make no doubt, but fully conclude, that others are as well bound as you are, to inform Magiſtrates of notorious Offenders known to them; even as <hi>all ought</hi> (in their Places) <hi>to promote the due Execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Juſtice;</hi> but you have a great ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of other ſingle Perſons, as being aſſociated, and having got into ſo good a method. That any ſingle Perſon may ſay here, <hi>What am I able to do in compariſon of you?</hi> (tho' others are not hereby excuſed, who will do nothing.) Now you <hi>doing your part,</hi> offering, or giving evidence againſt ſuch Offenders, if a Magiſtrate ſhall neglect or refuſe to puniſh them, <hi>the ſin will lie at his door, not at yours.</hi> But bleſſed be God, you have Magiſtrates, who have counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanc'd and encourag'd you in this neceſſary work, from your very firſt undertaking it.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:152820:22"/> (3.) Conſider, are you not under the Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation of Divine Precept to diſcover ſuch Sin and Wickedneſs, and expoſe it to due Puniſhment? As an eminently Learned Man obſerves, <q>The charge of puniſhing great Offenders is given to the Community. <hi>Thou,</hi> every individual, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.18. <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a Witch to live.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>And hath not God made that which you have undertaken, a Duty, where the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary is forbidden or condemn'd; and where other plain, unqueſtionable Duty cannot otherwiſe be perform'd. The Iſraelites were expreſly charg'd not to conceal an Enticer to Idolatry, <hi>Deut.</hi> 13.8. <hi>Neither ſhalt thou conceal him.</hi> And the reaſon againſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealing notorious Offenders is the ſame here, as there; <hi>viz.</hi> if ſuch be conniv'd at, and ſuffered to go on in their Wickedneſs, <hi>their wicked Practices and Impunity</hi> together, will certainly tend to corrupt others, and encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage others in the like Wickedneſs. Again, where the People are reprov'd, that <hi>none called for Juſtice,</hi> Iſa. 59.4. this is very ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, that if it were not <hi>a Duty to call for Juſtice</hi> on Delinquents, if not a Duty to bring Offenders to Juſtice; there had been no juſt cauſe to lay this to their charge, as their ſin, as a <hi>culpable neglect,</hi> that none called for Juſtice. Again, what Man is there (that believes his Bible) that can deny, but thoſe ſins, which you endeavour to get ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs'd,
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:152820:22"/>if they commonly go unpuniſh'd, <hi>make way for God's dreadful Judgments</hi> to break in upon a Land? Then, ought you not to do what in you lieth to <hi>make up the Hedg?</hi> And are you not this way <hi>ſtanding in the Gap</hi> for the Land? Now can you at all queſtion, whether that be not your Duty? Are you in any doubt or ſuſpence, whether that be more than the Lord requires, more than needs? then conſult, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 22.30.</p>
            <p>Again, is it not God's expreſs charge, that we <hi>partake not of others ſins;</hi> that we <hi>have no fellowſhip with the unfruitful works of Darkneſs,</hi> but <hi>rather reprove them,</hi> Eph. 5.7, 11. And 'tis not enough that you joyn not in Fellowſhip with the wicked; but you muſt ſhew your <hi>diſlike</hi> of their wicked Courſes, and that in the moſt likely way to ſtop them. Now meer <hi>verbal Reproof is not likely to do good</hi> on Beaſtly, Stupid, Hardned, Obſtinate Sinners; but <hi>like enough to do hurt, to work contrary to Intention,</hi> where Sinners are full of Malignity. In which caſes that <hi>general Rule</hi> takes place, <hi>Matth.</hi> 7. <hi>v.</hi> 6. <hi>Give not that which is Holy to the Dogs, neither caſt ye your Pearls before Swine.</hi> And ſee <hi>Prov.</hi> 9.7, 8. <hi>He that reproveth a Scorner, getteth to himſelf ſhame: And he that rebuketh a wicked Man, getteth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf a blot. Reprove not a Scorner, leſt he hate thee.</hi> Here more good, a better effect may be expected, by putting ſuch under the
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:152820:23"/>
               <hi>Rebukes of Juſtice,</hi> and the Civil Magiſtrate, at leaſt more benefit to others. <hi>Pro.</hi> 19.25. <hi>Smite a Scorner, and the ſimple will beware.</hi> chap. 21.11. <hi>When the Scorner is puniſhed, the ſimple is made Wiſe.</hi> Certainly, where Sinners are hardned and obſtinate, a verbal Reproof is not enough; nor will excuſe thoſe from partaking of their ſins, <hi>who might do more to reſtrain them,</hi> and do it not. See 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2.23, 24. compar'd with ch. 3.13. When all you can do is little enough to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain that Wickedneſs, which has ſo long abounded; Mourning <hi>in ſecret</hi> is not enough, nor a <hi>private</hi> Reproof, where you may meet with a Sinner, that ſeems not uncapable of receiving it. Alas! how many deſperate, impudent Sinners may you meet with, that would laugh at your Reproofs, as <hi>Leviathan</hi> is ſaid to <hi>laugh at the ſhaking of the ſpear:</hi> But as, <hi>Qui non prohibet, cùm poteſt, jubet.</hi> He that does not prohibit a thing, when he might, <hi>in effect</hi> wills and commands: So not oppoſing Sin and Wickedneſs, ſo far as one might, is <hi>interpretatively</hi> a maintaining or promoting it</p>
            <p n="4">(4.) Are you not oblig'd to ſet againſt ſin (in your Places) by your <hi>Baptiſmal Vow and Covenant:</hi> You are <hi>Chriſts liſted Soldiers:</hi> And I hope, in the work you have under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken, you are <hi>ſighting under his Banner,</hi> own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Cauſe, acting his Intereſt, and oppoſing the contrary Intereſts of the Fleſh,
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:152820:23"/>the World and the Devil. And how ſhall we <hi>prove our Loyalty</hi> and Fidelity to Chriſt, if we are not Enemies to ſin?</p>
            <p n="5">(5.) And ſhould you not follow your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers with ſuitable endeavours? To pray for Reformation; but to do nothing to promote it, what is that, but in effect to <hi>un-ſay ones Prayers?</hi> Shall I ſay, that is to contradict ones Prayers, or to undo them? To pray, <hi>[Hallowed be thy Name]</hi> and yet to take it patiently, tho' one hears God's Sacred and Reverend Name diſhonour'd and blaſphem'd: To pray <hi>[Thy Kingdom come]</hi> and yet not to appear againſt the Kingdom of Satan, the Kingdom of Darkneſs, as one might and ought: To pray [<hi>Thy Will be done on Earth,</hi> &amp;c.] and yet to ſuffer bold Heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daring Sinners to go on in their open Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion againſt God, and manifeſt Contempt of his holy Laws without controul, when one might bring them under ſome Reſtraint, or <hi>Legal Rebukes;</hi> how do theſe things agree? To pray, that the Wickedneſs of the Wicked may come to an end, and yet ſuffer Men to go on in their Wickedneſs, when one might put ſome ſtop to them, ſure, this is not right; but rather like <hi>ſaying ones Prayers backwards.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">(6.) Conſider, you have ſuch an oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity now offer'd, wherein to be active for God, and againſt the abounding Wickedneſs of the Age, which if you ſhould not lay
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:152820:24"/>hold on, you may never have the like again. How great encouragement you have to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear for a <hi>Reformation of Manners,</hi> having ſuch Laws and Rulers, Magiſtrates to coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance, and back you! And what excuſe could you have, if you ſat ſtill, at ſuch a time as this? Well, think of it, you may never have the like opportunity and advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage again (as now you have) of ſerving God and your Generation.</p>
            <p n="7">(7.) And know this, if you act ſincerely in this Buſineſs, the Lord will take it well, he will look on you, as ſerving him in your Generation. And how good is it to be at work for God? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 106.30, 31. <hi>Then ſtood up Phineas, and executed Judgment</hi> — And that <hi>was counted unto him for Righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</hi> The Lord accepted it, declared his Approbation of it, as a piece of Service, that ſhould not go unrewarded. Tho' it is not in your Hands to execute Judgment, yet 'tis ſomething, that you have Hearts to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote the execution of Juſtice. And while you are ſtanding up for God againſt the <hi>evil Doers,</hi> fear not, but he will be with you, and ſtand by you. And ſhall not your work be rewarded? God would reward <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar</hi> and the Babylonians, as having wrought for him, ſerving his Providence, in being <hi>Inſtruments of inſlicting Judgment</hi> upon proud <hi>Tyre;</hi> whenas <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> and his Soldiers had <hi>no intention of ſerving
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:152820:24"/>God</hi> in the War, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 29.18, 19, 20. May not you hope, the Lord is <hi>better pleaſed with the Service</hi> you have undertaken? And he is the moſt bountiful Rewarder. And if greater Judgments ſhould be coming on a ſinful Kingdom, ſuch as ſeek Righteouſneſs may have hope to be <hi>hid in the day of the Lord's Anger.</hi> In times of Publick Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mities, they are ſafeſt, or may bear up beſt, who have the greateſt care not to partake of others ſins. It may be a great comfort to you in the worſt times, that can come, if you can approve <hi>your ſelves to be clear in this matter.</hi> But if more would joyn with you, or follow your Example, we might have ſome hope, that the <hi>Nations Guilt and Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger would be leſs.</hi> And ſo,</p>
            <p n="8">(8.) Conſider, you may this way be do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing great, good Service unto many others.</p>
            <p n="1">[1.] Thus 'tis poſſible, that the Sinners themſelves, whom you bring under the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bukes of Juſtice, may thereby be brought to a better paſs. It may <hi>tend to their Cure:</hi> So that they and theirs may fare better for you. Their Families, Wives and Children may fare better.</p>
            <p n="2">[2.] So likewiſe you may this way be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>friend others. As you heard before, <hi>Smite a Scorner, and the ſimple will beware.</hi> By your means, many may be preſerv'd, and <hi>kept from falling into the like Exorbitances and Enormities.</hi> And I doubt not, very much
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:152820:25"/>ſin has been prevented by you, which (had you ſat ſtill) would have been committed in this Place.</p>
            <p n="3">[3.] What a Bleſſing may you be to this Beloved Town? A place the Lord hath long watch'd over for good, hath eminently pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd, favour'd, and many ways bleſt. Yet Scornful, obſtinate Sinners were like enough to <hi>ſet the Town on fire.</hi> For <hi>wickedneſs burns as the fire,</hi> Iſa. 9.18. 'Tis of a deſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Nature, where it prevails, and no care is taken to ſuppreſs it: Even for that ſin of <hi>Sabbath-prophanation,</hi> the Lord threatned to <hi>kindle a fire in the Gates of</hi> Jeruſalem, that ſhould devour the Palaces thereof, and ſhould not be quench'd, <hi>Jer.</hi> 17.28. May this Place be long bleſt in her Magiſtrates, and bleſt in you, and others like you, aſſiſting them as <hi>good Watch-men,</hi> that may prevent the fire of God's Wrath breaking forth here.</p>
            <p n="4">[4.] Yea, <hi>England</hi> may fare better for you. You may be of the number of <hi>Englands beſt Friends.</hi> Indeed the Anger of the Lord ſeems not yet turned away from us. What hopes we had ſometimes of plenty, with our Peace? There was hope ſometimes the laſt Summer of a plentiful, and joyful Harveſt: when it hath been a ſad Harveſt in ſeveral places, that we hear of. <hi>How long ſhall the Land mourn for the Wickedneſs of them that dwell therein?</hi> If the Sword of Juſtice be not drawn againſt ſin and ſinners, may
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:152820:25"/>we not then expect, that the Lord's hand will take hold on Judgment? <hi>A day of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dulgence</hi> towards Sinners is a <hi>day of Provo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation;</hi> and that is like to uſher in a day of Wrath and Calamity.</p>
            <p>But as it is in the Text, [<hi>Eſtabliſh Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Gate; it may be, that the Lord God of Hoſts will be gracious</hi> —.] When 'tis ſaid, <hi>[it may be]</hi> if we ſhould take the word as a particle of doubting; yet the doubt is not on God's part, but on Mans part; or 'tis an intimation of the difficulty of the thing to excite them to greater diligence in their Duty: Or 'tis not to diſcourage ſuch as hearken to God's Counſel; but to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courage others, who regard it not. If the righteous ſcarcely be ſaved, what will be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come of the wicked?</p>
            <p>But the due Execution of Juſtice is one good means to prevent Gods Judgments, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.11. <hi>Phineas hath turn'd my Wrath away from the</hi> Children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (<hi>while he was zealous for my ſake</hi> —.</p>
            <p>If any object, There are other Places, Countries in the World, where Sin and Wickedneſs abounds as much, as in <hi>England,</hi> that yet have Peace and Proſperity for all that.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. What tho' they proſper at pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent? yet you know not how ſoon dreadful Calamities may come upon them, and a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction from the Almighty. The <hi>Sun ſhone
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:152820:26"/>upon Sodom</hi> that very Morning, before fire and brimſtone was ſhower'd down from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, that deſtroyed them all. We uſe to ſay, <hi>Praiſe a fair day at night.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. And hath not God from Age to Age declar'd his Wrath againſt the Ungodlineſs and Unrighteouſneſs of Men, by his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments inflicted in one place or other? As is ſaid of <hi>Edom,</hi> Mal. 1.3, 4. <hi>I hated</hi> Eſau, <hi>and laid his Mountains, and his Heritage waſte: — And they ſhall call them, The Border of Wickedneſs, and the People againſt whom the Lord hath indignation for ever.</hi> And will you make nothing of thoſe dreadful Earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quakes, that of late made ſuch ruinating work in ſome Places? Or will you make nothing of the late Wars abroad, whereby ſo great Deſolations have been made in the Earth?</p>
            <p n="3">3. But further take notice, the Lord will rather, or will longer bear <hi>with other Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> forbear to puniſh the Wickedneſs of other Nations; than the Wickedneſs of a Nation, that hath been brought nearer to him, and is called by his Name, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg'd with his Word and Ordinances, <hi>&amp;c. Ingentia beneficia, flagitia, Supplicia.</hi> As ſuch a People are under greater Obligations, their ſins have higher Aggravations, and God is more diſhonoured by them, that they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve greater Puniſhment: And ſee <hi>Amos</hi> 3. ver. 2. <hi>You only have I known of all the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:152820:26"/>of the Earth: therefore I will puniſh you for all your Iniquities.</hi> And may not the Lord ſay thus of us? What Nation upon the face of the Earth, under the Cope of Heaven, that hath been more pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledg'd and more car'd for by the Lord, for whom God hath wrought greater Deliveran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, to whom he hath vouchſafed greater means, helps and advantages, than we of this Nation have had, to make us better? Theſe things duly conſidered, will ſhew our ſins of a <hi>deeper dye,</hi> and more provoking and threat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Upon which account, they deſerve well of <hi>England;</hi> ſure they are her moſt truſty <hi>Friends,</hi> who ſet themſelves vigorouſly againſt ſin. And therefore, I beſeech you, let not our <hi>Gracious Sovereign</hi> (for whom we pray, that he may long live, and reign proſperouſly, let him not) <hi>fare worſe;</hi> let not the <hi>Kingdom fare worſe</hi> for any Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs committed, which you are in any ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacity to prevent, or put a ſtop to. So far as you can hinder any further <hi>Accumulation</hi> to the Nations Sin and Guilt, (which is ſo great already, and lieth ſo heavy on it) let not your care and pains be wanting. You are in a way, in an hopeful way, with the encouragement and concurrence of your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates, to do ſomething towards the refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming of thoſe evil, Manners of an untoward Generation: Now be couragious and active. It may be a means to divert Judgment; yea,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:152820:27"/>it may be a <hi>Token for good,</hi> that the <hi>Lord</hi> will be further gracious to us, will be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to the Land.</p>
            <p>Now give me leave to ſpeak a little to two or three Objections, and I ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude.</p>
            <p>Object. 1. <hi>Some count you</hi> Buſie-bodies, <hi>meddling in matters that concern you not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Now how ſtrange is this? Do ſuch underſtand what they ſay? Should you not be concern'd for the <hi>Honour of God;</hi> and for the Peace and Welfare of the King and his Realm, for the Land of your Nativity; and for the Souls of others, even of bold, daring Sinners themſelves? Does not Sin and Wickedneſs, <hi>committed with Impudence and Impunity,</hi> ſtrike deſperately at all theſe? Then where were your Zeal for God, Loyalty to our King, love to your Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, compaſſion towards the Souls of Men, if you ſhould look upon your ſelves as un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>concern'd here? But if you <hi>ſet your ſelves as in the fore-front of the Battle,</hi> againſt the Vices, Wickedneſs and Prophaneneſs of the preſent Age; that would ſeem to argue, that you have a clearer, <hi>deeper Senſe of your Duty,</hi> than moſt Men have. And indeed ſome muſt do it, if any thing be done to purpoſe. And your Forwardneſs herein may provoke others to their Duty, who are hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto lagging behind.</p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:152820:27"/>
            <p> And as for thoſe who call you <hi>Buſie-Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> for endeavouring to put a ſtop to open Wickedneſs; ſuppoſe their Houſes were on fire, would they call you ſo, for coming to quench the fire? Or would they ſay to you, (Gentlemen, Friends,) <hi>Pray go Home and look to your own Houſes; you have nothing to do here?</hi> Now certainly, the prevailing of Wickedneſs in any place is of more dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous, and worſe conſequence, than a fire breaking forth in the Town.</p>
            <p>Object. 2. <hi>You make your ſelves</hi> Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> And what then? It is one thing to <hi>inform againſt Men for Religion, for Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Preaching, Hearing God's Word;</hi> and another thing to <hi>inform againſt Men for no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torious Irreligion, and Prophaneneſs, for Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and Swearing,</hi> &amp;c. It is one thing to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form againſt ſuch as were Pious and Peace<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able in the Land, <hi>out of Malice or of Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>touſneſs,</hi> to prey on their Eſtates, and raiſe themſelves on the Ruines of Men, more righteous than themſelves; and quite ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thing to inform againſt groſs Wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs out of <hi>Conſcience;</hi> not for any worldly Advantage; and ſeeking the Good of the Offenders themſelves.</p>
            <p>And I hope, the Objectors will not ſay, that <hi>Joſeph</hi> did amiſs, when he told of his Brethren, when he <hi>brought unto his Father
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:152820:28"/>their evil Report,</hi> in order to the Reforming of them, <hi>Gen.</hi> 37.1. And they that brought the Son of <hi>Shelomith</hi> to <hi>Moſes,</hi> for blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Name of the Lord, and Curling, [<hi>Lev.</hi> 24.11.] no doubt thought it would have been a great ſin in them, had they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nived at, and concealed ſuch Wickedneſs.</p>
            <p>And others have well obſerv'd, That the Princes thought it not below them, to be Informers in a caſe of this Nature, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9.1, 2.</p>
            <p>Again, this is plain, They that are againſt your informing Magiſtrates of the Breach of our good and wholeſom Laws, (how, and by whom they are broken) theſe, I ſay, are againſt <hi>eſtabliſhing Judgment in the Gate.</hi> For how ſhould wholeſom Laws be put in execution, without ſuch Information given to Magiſtrates? The greateſt Tranſgreſſors would be far from coming to accuſe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves. They would think themſelves ſafe enough, if there was no Puniſhment to be inflicted on them, but upon their <hi>confeſſion of the Fact.</hi> And ſuch, if they have a knowledge of Magiſtrates, that are for keeping up the Authority of the Law, and for executing Juſtice on Offenders; they would be moſt ſhy of them, that they be not taken tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſing <hi>within their view.</hi> So that <hi>Bar In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formations,</hi> and then the <hi>Sword of Juſtice might ruſt in the Scabbard;</hi> or however, it would be ſo ſeldom drawn, as to be no <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:152820:28"/>to evil Doers.</hi> When not one Offender of Ten, of Twenty, or of Forty, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> were like to fall under the laſh of the Law; this would be no great terror (to be ſure) to an Offender, that thinks it is forty to one, he ſhall eſcape.</p>
            <p>Again, let any indifferent Perſon judge, whether theſe Men be not partial? No doubt, they would have you <hi>ready to inform</hi> them, and ready to witneſs for them, and <hi>in their Cauſe,</hi> if you knew who had wrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed them, who had robb'd them, who had ſtolen a Horſe of theirs, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but they would have you to be <hi>mute in God's Cauſe.</hi> Now what is this, but to love and honour them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves above God; and to prefer their own petty Intereſts before the Intereſt of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and before the Glory of the Great God? As if it was <hi>a greater matter,</hi> that they ſhould be injured in the leaſt; than that Religion ſhould ſuffer, and the Name of God be never ſo highly diſhonoured.</p>
            <p>But be you aſſured, <q>
                  <hi>It will be found in the great day of Trial a greater Honour</hi> (as one ſays) <hi>to have been a faithful In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former againſt Vice, than a baſe conniver at it, and a wretched betrayer of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour of God and Religion.</hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="54" facs="tcp:152820:29"/>
            <p> Object. 3. <hi>Many of your Informations are Clandeſtine; and Offenders are oft convicted and puniſhed, without knowing their Accuſers. What ſhall we ſay to this?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Here it ſhould be conſidered, That it may be an <hi>Act of real Kindneſs,</hi> and Charity, to inform againſt common Swearers, Drunkards, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to bring them under the Rebuke of the Law and Juſtice (when there is no other likely means to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claim or reſtrain them from their wicked Courſes:) but it would be no kindneſs, it would do them no good, to let them know that you are the Perſons that inform'd againſt them; while it is likely to have ſuch ill effect, as to fill them with Wrath, Malice and Spite againſt you; and thus to <hi>increaſe their Sin and Guilt.</hi> Should you not avoid being Acceſſary to theſe other ſins of theirs; ſo far as you can prevent the occaſion, without neglecting your own Duty?</p>
            <p n="2">2. 'Tis both allowable and commendable, to uſe your beſt <hi>Prudence to keep off ill Turns,</hi> (without wronging Conſcience, without ſtaining your Innocence, your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity.) As you may pray to be deliver'd from wicked and unreaſonable Men, ſo you ſhould not unneceſſarily lay your ſelves
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:152820:29"/>open to their Spite and Revenge, <hi>Pro.</hi> 17.12. <hi>Let a Bear robb'd of her Whelps meet a Man, rather than a Fool in his Folly.</hi> It ſeems a raging Bear is a leſs dangerous Creature, than ſome furious Fools? 'Tis good to keep out of their way, when you can, without de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clining the way of your Duty. There are Sons of <hi>Belial, like Thorns, that can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be taken with Hands. But the Man that ſhall touch them, muſt be fenced with Iron, and the Staff of a Spear,</hi> 2 Sam. 23.6, 7. There are notorious Offenders, who ſufficiently declare their malignity againſt, and abhorrence of any zealous Magiſtrate, or faithful Miniſter, or others, that would take them off from their wicked Courſes.</p>
            <p>Now <hi>'tis not fit,</hi> that the Crimes of ſuch ſhould be conceal'd, but that they be diſcovered to thoſe, who, by their Place and Office, are to puniſh evil Doers. But <hi>'tis not neceſſary,</hi> that you do it ſo, as to exaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate and enrage them againſt you; when the end may be as well obtain'd by your giving private Information.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As (I believe) none of you could ever yet be juſtly charged with giving any <hi>falſe Information</hi> againſt any one; and there is no reaſon to ſuppoſe, that you would or durſt do it, (which could be no advantage to you; but if the party inform'd againſt, (being innocent, and falſly accuſed) ſhould
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:152820:30"/>enter Traverſe, and prove you perjur'd, would bring upon you ſo far greater Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment and Damage, than what you can think of bringing him under by your In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation againſt him) ſo the Premiſes being duly weigh'd and conſider'd, it may be thought prudent and very commendable, (as our times are) That Magiſtrates do not make known the Names of particular In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formants, without juſt and neceſſary Cauſe. Surely 'tis pitty that faithful Informers ſhould be diſcourag'd, needleſly expoſed to others hatred, and ill will, for doing their Duty, and for their good Will to the Nation in general; yea, and to the Offen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders themſelves, whoſe Reformation is aimed at. Yea, how can a good Magiſtrate ſatisfie himſelf to do that which he knows the Law doth not require, <hi>when it is not likely to do good, but hurt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Were it not to be wiſhed, that they who have nothing to ſay againſt your infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Magiſtrates of notorious Offenders; but only they would have all your Infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations as open, as the Offences committed (I ſay, were it not to be wiſh'd that theſe) would come in now, and help to <hi>break the Ice?</hi> Let them now ſhew their Zeal for the due Execution of Juſtice, (and the more of them, ſtill the better.) So let them have the <hi>Honour to be of the Thirty;</hi> tho' ſomething
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:152820:30"/>ſhort of the <hi>firſt three.</hi> Such would do great Service, when by an open appearance againſt thoſe deteſtable Sins and Vices of the Times, (where they have the Law on their ſide) they may provoke others, all that are <hi>Eye or Ear-witneſſes</hi> of ſuch Crimes committed, and that would not partake of others ſins by concealing and conniving at them, in like manner to appear againſt them. Were the Practice more general and common, there would be leſs occaſion of informing privately; as the private Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venge of Offenders were leſs to be fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed.</p>
            <p>Now to conclud: You are <hi>engaged in a good Cauſe.</hi> You have both the Law of God, and Man's Laws for your <hi>Warrant;</hi> hold on, be of good Courage. Indeed I cannot think, how you ſhould have any Enemies; but ſuch as are <hi>Enemies to God, and to the Publick Weal.</hi> And carrying uprightly, you may be ſure, you have <hi>God and Conſcience your Friends.</hi> You are doing your part to eſtabliſh Judgment in the Gate, and thus ſtanding in the Gap, to keep off God's Judgments. You have a great <hi>ſtock of Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers going forward for you;</hi> that you may have God's good Providence over you, his gracious Guidance and his Preſence with you; and that you may have happy ſucceſs in your ſo worthy Undertaking. Your good Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:152820:31"/>has had a <hi>good influence</hi> upon ſome other Places; and, I hope, will have on more; and even on ſome Country-Towns, or Villages about you. After all, be the ſucceſs more or leſs, yet making it your care to approve your Hearts to God, being ſuch indeed as <hi>hate the Evil, and love the Good,</hi> you may reſt aſſured, That <hi>your Reward is with the Lord.</hi> But further, may not your acting and going on unanimouſly (as others likewiſe in the Chief City of our Land, and elſewhere) notwithſtanding your being of different Perſwaſions in ſome leſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſer Matters; I ſay, may not this be a good <hi>Omen,</hi> (if the Lord will yet delight in <hi>England</hi>) that all ſuch as agree in the main and neceſſary Points of Religion, ſhall come in time (waving their leſſer Differences) heartily to unite, ſo as to <hi>ſtrengthen the true Intereſt of Chriſtianity againſt all its Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies;</hi> that true Piety and Chriſtian Charity may flouriſh amongſt us; that Iniquity may ſtop its Mouth, and all Impiety and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaneneſs hide the Head. And happy <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> if <hi>this War begun againſt</hi> Prophane<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>ſhall be ſo bleſt and proſper'd, as to end in our</hi> Jeruſalems <hi>Peace.</hi> I ſay again, hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py <hi>England,</hi> if ſhe ſhould at laſt become <hi>an Example of Reformation,</hi> as to Mens Lives and Practices, unto other Churches <hi>Reform'd in Doctrine,</hi> where yet (as to Manners) there are many things to be reform'd. Were
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:152820:31"/>
               <hi>England</hi> herein an Example to them, then, might we not hope, That ſhe ſhould be a <hi>Crown of Glory in the hand of the Lord,</hi> and a <hi>Royal Diadem in the hand of her God?</hi> Yea, ſo ſhould our <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> be renown'd indeed, be a <hi>praiſe in the Earth.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:152820:32"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A</hi> Catalogue <hi>of</hi> Books <hi>printed for</hi> Tho. Parkhurſt, <hi>at the</hi> Bible <hi>and</hi> Three Crowns, <hi>the lower end of</hi> Cheapſide, <hi>near</hi> Mercers Chappel.</head>
            <p>MR. <hi>Howe</hi>'s Sermon for Reformation of Manners.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Spademan</hi>'s Sermon for Reformation of Manners.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Golden Snuffers:</hi> A Sermon for Reformation of Manners: Preach'd by Dr. <hi>Durgeſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Holy Confidence well improv'd by <hi>Nehe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miah and the Jews.</hi> A Sermon for Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of Manners; By Mr. <hi>Sylveſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>All four Preach'd to the</hi> Societies <hi>in and about</hi> London.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152820:32"/>
            <p> A Sermon preach'd to the Society for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of Manners, at the Pariſh-Church of St. <hi>Mary</hi> in <hi>Nottingham:</hi> By Mr. <hi>Daniel Chadwick,</hi> Vicar of <hi>Arnhal,</hi> and one of the Lecturers there.</p>
            <p>Mr. <hi>VVhitlock</hi>'s Sermon, preach'd to the Society for Reformation of Manners in <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Sermons and Diſcourſes on ſeveral Divine Subjects, <hi>Folio;</hi> by <hi>David Clarkſon,</hi> B.D. and ſometimes Fellow of <hi>Clare-Hall, Cambridge.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Diſcourſe of Saving Grace.</p>
            <p>Of Free Juſtification: Written in Latine by <hi>John Fox.</hi> And now made Engliſh.</p>
            <p>The Fountain of Life open'd: Or, a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>play of Chriſt in his Eſſential and Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torial Glory; containing 42 Sermons on va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Texts. By <hi>J. Flavel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Treatiſe of the Soul of Man.</p>
            <p>—His Method of Grace, in bringing home the Eternal Redemption, contrived by the Father, and accompliſh'd by the Son, thro' the effectual Application of the Spirit unto God's Elect.</p>
            <p>—Husbandry Spiritualized, or the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Uſe of Earthly Things.</p>
            <p>—His Token for Mourners for the death of Friends.</p>
            <p>—His Saint indeed; [the great Work of a Chriſtian.</p>
            <p>—His two Treatiſes, Firſt, Of Fear: Secondly, Of the righteous Man's Refuge in the evil Day.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:152820:33"/>
            <p> —His Touchſtone of Sincerity: Or, Signs of Grace, and Symptoms of Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy. Being the 2d part of, <hi>A Saint indeed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>—His Navigation Spiritualized: Or, a new Compaſs for Sea men; conſiſting of 32 Points of pleaſant Obſervations, profitable Applications, ſerious Reflections, all conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded with ſo many ſpiritual Poems, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>— His Divine Conduct, or Myſtery of Providence; its Being and Efficacy aſſerted and vindicated, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A Paraphraſe upon the New Teſtament, with <hi>Notes, Doctrinal and Practical,</hi> fitted for the Uſe of Religious Families. By R. <hi>Baxter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of Charity in reference to other Mens. By Mr. <hi>How.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That Great Duty, and Comfortable Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, <hi>[Keeping our ſelves from our own Iniquity.]</hi> Opened and applied in ſome Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons upon <hi>Pſal.</hi> 18.23. By <hi>John VVhitlock,</hi> Miniſter in <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A ſhort Account of the Life of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Mr. <hi>William Reynolds.</hi> By <hi>John Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>look.</hi> To which is added, his Funeral Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon; preach'd by <hi>John Barrat,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel in <hi>Nottingham.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Carnality of Religious Contention. In <hi>two Sermons preach'd at the Merchants Lecture in</hi> Broad-ſtreet. By the Reverend Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
